<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A consolatory letter, humbly addressed to her royal highness the Princess Anne of Denmark, upon the much lamented death of his most illustrious highness William Duke of Gloucester, August 2. 1700</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80374</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896225</idno>
  <idno type="VID">153879</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240917902</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5929A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230220</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896225</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99896225e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80374)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2386:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A consolatory letter, humbly addressed to her royal highness the Princess Anne of Denmark, upon the much lamented death of his most illustrious highness William Duke of Gloucester, August 2. 1700</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>Pp. 48+   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2386 lacking all after page 48.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Anne, --  Queen of Great Britain, 1665-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">William, --  Duke of Gloucester, 1689-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:153879:1"/>
            <head>A Consolatory Letter, humbly Addressed to Her Royal Highness the Princess <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> upon the much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented Death of His Most Illustrious Highness <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Gloucester, August</hi> 2. 1700.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MAY it Please Your Highness to forgive this Address (to Your Royalty) could Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness see the Glories the Duke now enjoys, You would be content to abate of your own Satisfaction for His Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance; God saw Him fit for Happiness; His Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty has taken him to fill up the Place of a Seraphin in His own Court; earthly Courts are mean compared to to that of Heaven; the Soul is so glorious a Creature, that we cannot yet know its Happiness; the Nation has lost their Hopes; but God can supply the Duke's Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from a new Off-spring, from the Original; Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; or if not we must submit that deserved Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: How sudden soever the Surprise was to Mortals, certainly 'twas Kindness in God to the Duke, to take him to be one of the Ravishing Companions with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; May it Please Your Highness to abate of your deep Sorrow, and contemplate on the Joys your Son does now possess. 'Tis not unlike, but that Your Highness would have been content to have parted with him a little for his greater Advance; since God is pleased this way to dignify him, 'tis to be supposed, that Your Highness is willing to yield to the Divine Will, nothing can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miss that God is pleased with, or sees good to do; Who can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce good out of that which we fear and feel to be evil? God is pleased with us when we submit to his Divine Pleasure; Could we see the Felicity that good Souls are now in, we should immediately wish our selves to be of their Company: The Soul of Man is the noblest of all God's Creatures; the Angels rejoyce at the reception of every holy Soul into the Bosom of their Maker; the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb facs="tcp:153879:2"/> was his, the Loss is only ours (O that Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness's inward Purity, Brightness and Honou<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, wou<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d be graciously pleased to forgive your offending Vassal) great is the Tenderness the late Melancholy Solemnity univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally inspired, the Shortness of that precious Life may be recompensed by an Immortal Memory; his Mind though young, conceived generous and noble Things; Silence is his highest Panegyrick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leave I crave, to add a Word or Two for the Encouragement of Proficients, and such as delight in the Exercise of Wisdom and Virtue, a comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Study. Science, without other Courtship than its own Merit, ought to be an especial Favourite of the Soul; and chiefly to be valued by the most emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of Men; a Motive of such high Importance, that it caused the Great <hi>Alexander</hi> to declare, That he had rather be a Prince of Science, than Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the vast Dominions possessed by him: Princes of superlative Esteem, have to their Glory promoted the Excellencies of Science, and are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly conspicuous in Records of Fame: If they have been Illustrious in their Sphere (the Court;) they have not judged themselves greater under a Canopy of State, than when their Grandeur has Flourished with the Encouragement and Growth of the Art of Knowledge; <hi>Aristotle,</hi> the Tutor of the Great <hi>Alexander,</hi> though famous for Learning, his Name nor Works had never been so far, diffused in the World, if his Pupil had not countenanced, encouraged, and assisted him by his Power. <q>The next great Example was <hi>Julius Caesar;</hi> who is mentioned by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> as a Parallel in Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and warlike Conquests, to the mighty <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander;</hi> but far surpassing the Conduct of his Arms, and Counsels of State; as to the perpetual Memorial of his Glory and Erudite Accomplishments, Men famous in Mathematical Science, were authorized by him to amend the then erroneous Computation of the Sun's Annual Revolution, to which at this Day, in the Julian Year, we own our Calendar, and the Month of <hi>July</hi> dedicated to his everlasting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153879:2"/> Renown, in the Year that was rectified by his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Command:</q> A Work transcending the greatest of his Earthly Fame, as to the height of the Sun, the Soveraign of Light; his Name is exalted in Story, for his Soveraign Dignity and vast Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of Mind; he was signally accomplished to patronize so sublime a Performance: His Skill was admirable, his Vigilancy and Experience employed to advance the Glory of God; Man is endow'd with Gifts of the Mind, above all other animated Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; so, the Grace of God and Diligence in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, do by its Excellency highly advance the use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Speculations and Comprehensions of one Man superior to another; Diligence and Sincerity in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is the Queen of Virtue; It directs to the highest Atchievements, of which, none can exceed the love of Truth, for that is the Guide and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of all the Virtues; it gives us a Prospect into the future World, and encourages Man to live worthy of obtaining the Virtues that shall give him a Title to be Heir of the invisible World: Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty is a leading Example, and an especial Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rager of such parts of useful Knowledge (<hi>i. e.</hi> true Devotion and Piety) as may embellish the Mind of Man, and erect it to its proper End, the subduing of Vice, and the love of Virtue; when a Man is arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at Truth, his Judgment will be refined, and he will be able to direct his Choice, and be a Leader of others in the way of Life; being your self divinely taught, you are a Light and a Guide to every teachable Genius, to love Truth and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion above all other Sciences, does advance the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Eyes and Heart, in order to the Divine Contemplation of the wonderful Movements and Beings of the Celestial Orbs, but above all to adore the God that made them; God has made us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible, and we see and admire him in all his Works; Science exalts our Intellects, and directs Man to his proper End, which is the Care of his Carriage in order to his future State; nothing is more commendable than the due Exercise of the
<pb facs="tcp:153879:3"/> Humane Mind; in such requisite Contemplations, as most effectually conduce to the Improvement of the Understanding, in things of special Importance, we exist in a World whose Structure is admirable, no less to our Speculation, than how we came to have a Being in it; or are originally ensouled above other Creatures: God has infused into us a Love of Goodness, if we improve the good Motions he has put into us; our Hearts will quickly be enflamed with Divine Love, and replenished with certain Beams of Glory and Divine Illumination; our Understanding will be elevated, and we shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from Virtue to Virtue, till we arrive to a good Proficiency in the School of Wisdom; a Soul disgusted with the World, meets with true Repose in God; Death that despoils the living of their Pomp, will cloath every holy Soul with new Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and fresh Glories, to them that by the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise and Practice of Wisdom have gained a habit of Devotion, and refers all their Virtues to the Glory of God; and he that does not this, is a false <hi>Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oso.</hi> But true Virtue raises and strengthens Mens Hearts, and makes them despise Death and Danger, when it is for an honourable End; and where the Glory of God calls and engages them to it; before whose Presence universal Nature trembles; to him therefore let us direct our Thoughts, and all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of our Minds and Bodies, as being confident of his Goodness and Acceptance; all Help and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistances is to be found in him; every Good is to be found in God; O great Majesty; Let me perfectly pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess thee, for thou art to me instead of every thing besides; the World has taken from me all it gave but nothing can rob me of thy Presence; Why should I so bitterly bewail the Loss of those that Death deprives me of? they were not mine but God's, h<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath exalted them beyond all earthly Honour; Go lent them me, but has now resumed them to him self; their now Felicity is beyond Expression; Wh<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> should I be uneasy on their behalf, seeing they ar<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>essed beyond Expression or present Conception
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153879:3"/> I will not renew my Sorrows with over-much an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xlousness concerning them, they are in rest and full Felicity; I will divinely prepare to be so too; but I may not renew your Sorrow, or provoke your Passion by a Panegyrick on our Deceased Friends, but rather ruminate upon the Felicity we aspire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by keeping an Inoffensive Conscience; we will not therefore gain Knowledge, or Wealth, or any Felicity whatsoever, by the loss of Innocency, O thou Source of all created Light, Penetrate to the inmost of my Heart, with one of thy Rays that may prevent my Fall; Purify and make me glad in thee; Enlighten and quicken my Soul and all its Faculties, and unite them to thy self, that by thy Grace, I may renew my Conference with thee, and daily receive Comfort from thee: <hi>Commerce with thee is better than Life; my Soul shall praise thee,</hi> Possess my Soul with a full hope of Glory, and of Felicity that will never end, or wear out; leave no place in me for any vain Imagination; let my Conceptions be only of thy Majesty and Beauty; let no mortal Law rule over the Law of my Understanding: I desire to serve thee with a Love all pure, let me once arrive to the solid Joy of thy glorious self; satisfie my Thirst after Righteousness, with the Blessing of a righteous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation. My Soul longeth after thy Courts, O when shall I see thy unvailed Felicity? Impart to me some of thy glorious Rays, give me an habitual Thought of Thee, be Thou always in my Mind and Intentions, I will frequently think on my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Death and Sepulchre, who for my sake en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Chambers of Death. Let every Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence advance me one step nearer Heaven; O that I could acceptably meditate on thee, guard me from all evil, spread in my Soul the Divine Rays of thy Grace; in all thy Works let me see thy Divinity shine forth, let all my Actions be Works worthy of Imitation. God alone is my Treasure and true Riches, the Delight of mine Eyes, and the Joy of my Soul; Suffer me never to do any thing unworthy of Piety. May all Men aspire after those who are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153879:4"/> placed with God, and inherit the Glory which is there, and in particular, the Prince the Nation have been lamenting; who is gone from hence to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for more sublime Glory, the Wisdom of Heaven excells all other Wisdom; Great Princess, May the Hand of God lead you in all your Counsels and Enterprizes; May your Wisdom be admired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove your Power, and your Power out-shine your wisdom, but your Piety over ballance both; May Your mighty Highness each Day become more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine in excelling in the Love of Christ, that the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py People under your Conduct, may become a shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Nation: May God ensure your Security and Sofety, and you be ever watchful for the Good of <hi>Christendom;</hi> the Value of Souls is countless, the Soul is a Jewel beyond Prize, till we begin to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon the Value our Lord paid, to rescue it from end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Thraldom; Learn we; from your Example; to supplicate God for its Safety, that we may lay hold on the Terms of Salvation, pointed out to us by the Gospel. Your Royal Piety is a leading Star, an Ornament to Religion. May it not offend Your Majesty that I presume, nameless, unmark'd, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, sunk by Birth and Fate, and lower yet by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal Fortune's Weight.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>LOrd be merciful to all who are true Parts and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the one true Catholick and Apostolick Church, and on all those which differ from the ancient Truth; make us all one Sheep sold under our great Sheapherd and Bishop Christ Jesus, that we may all give thee due Honour and Praise, according to the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of thy great Majesty; O compleat that Promise of giving by Son the Heathen for his Heritage, and the utmost Parts of the Earth for his Pessessions, that we may all be gathered under thy sure Mercies, and when time shall fail, be admitted to behold thy Face in Glory; these Mercies we beg for the Merits of our dear Redeemer, to whom with thee O Father, and the glorious Spirit, be all Honour and Glory, World without End,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153879:4"/>
            <head>To the Judicious Reader.</head>
            <p>THE Reader may here find hard Arguments delivered in soft Words; the End at which it aims, will compensate for the defect of Stile and Method; which invites to pursue as our chief End, invisible Bliss, attainable by all that pursue it with an eager and thirsty Mind; the Thought of living for ever, is such a Motive as is able to make a Man defie all Difficulties, so far as to be inflamed the more by the Apprehension of them, and to stick at nothing but flat Impossibilities; but this cannot be objected by a wise Man in the case, it may be difficult or uneasy to our present Delights and Pleasures; it is plain in experience, that many Men have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone greater Hardships, than any the Gospel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, either to demonstrate their love, or to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue their Passion, in compliance with their Fears, or for the sake of their Interests, for self-security or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of some Person, and always for Preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; now whatsoever may be done upon these inconsiderable Grounds, most certainly cannot be impossible, when eternal Life is at stake; Hope is the great Wager of him that runs, and cannot be obtained upon any other Terms; Hope, and Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of arriving at our desired End, must needs make the Yoke of Christ comparatively easie; let each Man then frame himself by the Rule of God's Word, that he may be capable of the Inheritance prepared for all the Lovers of God, the best that a wicked Man can hope for, is to rot in his Grave, and be everlastingly forgotten (and besides this suffer eternal Fire) but those that live by the Rule of the Gospel, shall undoubtedly be raised out of the Dust, and out-live the very Heavens in unspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and endless Felicity; for God is a necessary Being, and must live for ever, as the following Tract asserts; he made all things by his Power out of nothing, and by the same Power, will raise the Dead again out of the Dust; this is the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153879:5"/> of the Gospel of which we have Assurance, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 31. and after this Assurance, who can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of Difficulty, considering the Joys in view ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, considering also the Assistance the Gospel affords us, towards the performing the Duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; to which we may add, that Christianity is now become the Religion of our <hi>English</hi> Empire, and is defended and encouraged by it; God also com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates to us his holy Spirit, which co-operates with us to qualifie us for the glorious Rewards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, by spiritual Worship, purity of Heart, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversal Charity; the Divine Power will co-operate with us to discharge these, and this being our happy Case, how can there by any such thing as Impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, nor scarcely so much as Difficulty, for what can be impossible to Almighty Power, or who can complain of Burthen that hath such an Helper; we have the Benefit of common Providence to uphold and strengthen our Minds, and the Effects of spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Providence in removing Obstacles, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our way easie, by the vital Power and Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Divine Spirit, by which our Minds are daily more enlightned, to see the Excellency of this Undertaking; and our Will is confirmed in the Choice of this Resolution, and our Affections quickned in the pursuit and execution of this Choice, and our Hearts exceedingly cheared in the whole En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize with unspeakable Joy, and with the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and ravishing Prospect of the Glory that shall attend and crown our Performances, which we shall receive, when the whole Seminary of the Church Triumphant, shall be gathered in one vast Body, in the future World; which is an Encouragement to assemble our selves in the present Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Seminary of this Church, which is now Militant; and it is ridiculous to object Difficulty against this glorious Institution; the Design of the following Pages are noble and generous, namely, to heighten and confirm our Belief of the Glories to come, in reserve for all that will diligently seek to attain them; we demonstrate that the strictest Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153879:5"/> are consistent with the greatest Prudence and Civility; we Essay to raise the dejected and depres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Spirit of Piety in the World. Great is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of Religion and Virtue. Here the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Religion is searched into, and particularly, that great point concerning a Judgment to come, is substantially proved; and the Wisdom of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Religion as well the Subject of social Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, as of retired Meditation; here is warm and sensible Discourse of another World, and of the necessary Preparations for it, whereby a Man's Heart may be inflamed with Devotion, which if neglected, cannot be but with very ingrateful Returns to the Divine Bounty; which have made liberal and ample provisions for the Delight and Contentment of all Men, whereby the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty have obliged us to Obedience, and would have all Men fix and improve their Minds to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects suitable to their Capacities, that they may fill up the vacant spaces of their time, with delightful and profitable Entertainments for the Good of their Souls, that they give no occasion of Scandal by any misbecoming Action; that the Accent of the Speech be not fierce nor violent, but Candour sh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w good Example unto all, throughout the whole Demeanour of their Life, that they may not be over positive and decretal in their Assertions, nor define with too great Confidence; they are not Privy-Counsellers of Heaven, nor are their Definitions and Determinations always true; some Men can talk well, and set a good Face upon that which they have no comfortable Sense of, and no Wonder if such M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns Courage fail them when they have most use for it, for it is not imaginable that it should be easie to brazen it out against Death, but this is no more reproach to true Faith in God, and hopes of fature Bliss, than it is to generous Courage and Valour; it is easie to brag and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our when no Danger is near, but it requires real Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to stand to it, when a Man is briskly encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; there are Men that dare to be virtuous in a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153879:6"/> lewd Age, and evil Company, and hath the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to confront the whole World with their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; there are Men that can want without repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and be liberal without upbraiding; that can bear Prosperity without being lifted up, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity without being dejected, which show them to be brave and worthy Persons; neither will they be discomposed at the rude Assaults of Death; which if they were, it might not blemish their Faith nor Virtue, in regard that naturally all Men have a Love of Life, and an Abhorrence of Death; and from hence may proceed some sudden Reluctances, because it is neither in the power of Reason, nor in the Office of Religion, utterly to exterminate and extinguish these first Motions, but to subdue and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them; so that a Man may after some Conflict pursue the choice of his Mind, notwithstanding them; a violent Disease or Pain, or any of those fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of Death, do ordinarily enfeeble the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the Mind, as well as the Body; and sometimes disorder their Reason, that it is hard to pronounce of their Courage at that time, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat they then maintain; but when we see a Man in his full Strength, voluntarily and understandingly do any noble Exploit, this hath certainly Bravery and Self denial in it, Contempt of Life and the World; and is a greater Argument of Hopes in the other World, than can be drawn from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies in the very Agony of Death: Upon which Thought, a Man that has been cold and indifferent in Religion, may on the sudden be inflamed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured with the bright Idea of it; it is the last and ultimate Revelation of the Divine Will, and is exact and perfect; it repeals no Law of Nature or Reason, it derogates from no Rule of Piety, Gratl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, Civility or Humanity, but adds to them and improves them: The Christian Institution is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st of all that is grave, decent, prudent, virtuous, or praise-worthy; it injoyns a most excellent and spiritual Worship, such as must be accompanied with refined Purity of Heart and Life, it raises and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153879:6"/> improves the State of Mankind, it inflames the Mind to the Love of God, and encourages our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours proportionably, it gives Assurance by Faith in Jesus, of attaining the glorious Design of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming our selves, our Passions and Vices; the Books of the Scripture contain a very admirable Institution, all the noble Actions that have been done in the World, have taken their Rise from the Doctrine of these Books; they are a certain way of Information of what God requires and expects from us, and we may justly expect Satisfaction from them, how to acquire everlasting Life; where we understand them not aright, God will supply the Defect, by applying himself to the inward Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our Souls, by, the secret Operations of his holy Spirit, whereby he instills his Mind into Mens Hearts.</p>
            <p>God speaks to Men in his Word, the Word of God is quick and powerful, and sharper than any Two-edged Sword, piercing even to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding asunder both Soul and Spirit, this is a Discerner of the Thoughts and Intents of the Heart, this Word will certainly serve to the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to which it was ordained, God's Honour is as secure as his Happiness; it is the unbelieving only that will suffer; let not the wicked give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the vain Pleasure (if they will not be perswaded by the Gospel) to think to bring it in Disrepute, or disappoint its Author; for God is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his own Honour, and to crush in sunder those that <note n="*" place="margin">For the Subtilty Men use when they endeavour to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the great Truths of the Gospel are necessary Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it, for nothing but a thinking Mind could use that Subtilty, for it is impossible that Matter and Chance should forge and polish such subtil Notions.</note> oppose it, and go on in their old unchristian Course; they are glad to know how to make Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and object, and resolved are they not to obey, they will not be fully p<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rswaded it seems, sh<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld they see all the Dead arise, or the whole Host of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153879:7"/> come down, so little Fairh has our Lord found; at his Death he left not much, and he makes it a Question after, whether at his Return he shall find any; any proportionably to the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Messages of the Gospel, and to the Greatness and Dignity of its Power; yet however the Revelation is not disparaged, but verified by it; we are not surprized to sind, that there are such who neglect or contradict, these are those of whom we have been forewarned, that they will not be perswaded to save their own Souls from endless and everlasting Misery, though the Notice how to do it through the Mercy of God, is so plain and evident, that reasonably and in Duty they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand more, however more will not be granted; if the Convictions and Evidences God has afforded us, will not have a good Effect upon us, no other shall now be given; no other shall be sent from the Dead for our Conviction, till we our selves do rise to Judgment: If we will not believe <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets, we are past Remedy, the Book is sealed, as the Gulph below is fixed: And those that will not be prevailed upon by this Method, they will not, they shall not have any other extended to them, the Son of God and his Apostles have pleaded to them, there will be no further Endeavour to perswade them: <hi>If the Gospel be hid, it is hid to those that are lost,</hi> take we heed how we despise the Admonition of <hi>Him that is risen from the Dead,</hi> and now speaks from Heaven, <hi>our Maker, our Redeemer, and our Judge,</hi> this Life is the time to hear the Directions of God, and to comply with his Wisdom for our Salvation; in the great Day of Audience we shall be called to hear his Sentence, and to confess his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice; and then a knowing Age will be the most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper to plead Ignorance, who amongst us will dare to say he wanted Notice? the perswaded and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perswaded will then have their different Portions, and be set at a wide distance, and we shall be either comforted or tormented, when the wise and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, <hi>small and great shall stand before God to give an
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153879:7"/> Account of themselves to him; when the Judgment will be set, and the Books shall be opened, and the dead shall be judged out of those Books,</hi> Revel. 21. 27. <hi>Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour the Brightness of God's Glory,</hi> has himself brought down from Heaven Information to us, infinitely surpassing what was spoke to the Fathers by <hi>Moses and the Proplsets,</hi> has laid open to us the World to come, and given a free Prospect of the Two diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent States; here the Sceptick may receive Advice, and the Man of Pleasures learn to use them law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and the Man of Business allot some Time that may prove seasonable for the Worship of God and religious Retirement, and have regard to all the Commands of God, which tend to <hi>original Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and Righteousness, both to God and to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> which is a true Knowledge of God in our Minds, and a Power and Inclination, and a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire in our Will and Heart, and in all our Parts to obey God, that we never cover nor bury the Truth, but declare it to the Honour and Praise of God; and for the inward Benefit and Satisfaction of Men, we are bound to honour such as have been Instruments of God's Blessings to us, yet so as to praise God in them, and them in God; such as have <hi>been burning and shining Lights in the Church, famous in their Generation for Piety and Virtue; of these the People ought to speak of their Wisdom, and the Congregation of their Praise, Eccles.</hi> 4. 1. 2. 44. since our Requital cannot reach up to God, our glorious Head; we bestow our Ointment, our Gifts and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours upon his Feet, his poor Members here below.</p>
            <p>Conscience is not to be totally drowned in Drink, nor the Clamour thereof to be deaded by the Noise of Huzza's, the Mirth of a Debauch, as it is straitned and artificial, so it cannot last long; it is at the best but like the Effects of a strong Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial, which may serve to rally the Spirits for some present Encounter, but when they are spent in the Conflict, they fall and flag again quickly after, or like those mighty Efforts, which we may observe some Persons to make in a Convulsion, the Result of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153879:8"/> which will be, that such a Man shall become so much less than himself after the Fit, as he was more than himself whilst it was upon him, for any Man shall find, that whensoever the Spirits are extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily exhilarated and dilated, they thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come so thin and volatiley that they easily exhale and vanish, and so a Man becomes far more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy and lumpish after than he was before, but in intellectual Delights and Entertainments, a Man may be merry and wise together, and so have no Dread upon his Spirits to pall the present Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for religious Pleasures are without Fear or Danger, they afford a still and sedate Delight, which refreshes the Heart more than dilate the Countenance, and gently raise and strengthen the Spirits, but do not in any Measure exhaust them, a wise Man will therefore restrain himself in the use of bodily Pleasures, and flie as much as may be without Prejudice to those in Authority, publick Employments, as a Derogation to Wisdom, and a Disturber of Peace and Quietness, avoiding all distractive Cares, which may interrupt our spiritual Peace and Quietness, or impede us in our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Race, irreligious Practices do naturally produce irreligious Opinions, and the Disbelief of the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Peing, proceeds from a vicious Practice.</p>
            <p>Conscience before 'tis seared or hardned, will startle at Wickedness, but when Men are arrived at that height, that they can deny all first Principles they are then without a Miracle, beyond all pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibility of Conviction, for still demanding Proof after Proof, they must reel on to Eternity without Satisfaction, such contradicting Animals put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in a condition past Conviction, 'tis hard to find a Worthy that will take so long a Journey, or so fruitless a Trouble that will attempt to win them to Reason, since they are found to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to Diffidence, such is the Face of a Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick as it is drawn by his own Hand, he has made himself Proof against Conviction, he is a perverse sort of Creature resolved to contradict, he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153879:8"/> in all the studied Modes of Foolery, Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticism according to their own Definition, in its Effect, is Freedom from Assent, they have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Method to be true to their Folly, which may be exposed, but to endeavour to bring him to Sense or Reason, is a wild Design, all Advice to him is false and visionary: He that would establish the true Belief of the Deity, is certain to have the Sceptick for his Enemy, he being no less so to all revealed Religion, which derives it Authority from the supreme Lawgiver, which is the Being of Beings that bestows all Good, he that first mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Matter, is the free Agent and Giver of all things, and can carry one, or cease his Operations as he pleases, and will to the end of Time govern and direct, he orderly by Method preserves the Frame he at first raised, he is an allwise Director, discovering Rules, how Man may be endlesly happy.</p>
            <p>True Virtue fills the Consciences with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Peace and heavenly Light, it raises and strengthens Mens Hearts, and makes them run to Death, despise Dangers, and spare nothing where the Glory of God engages them, he that refers not all his Virtues to the Glory of God, is a false <hi>Virtuoso,</hi> but a Man that hath a true Taste of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, will always be forming his Mind by the Laws of Wisdom, and spend all his time in Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, furnishing himself with useful Knowledge and Virtue, which is chearing and delightful to the Mind. Knowledge enlarges the Soul, and adds Lustre to it, as pollishing does to a Jewel, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sullies and dims it, and makes it ugly, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge elevates the Mind, Ignorance depresses it, Knowledge tends to refine it from the Dregs of Sensuality, Ignorance leaves it polluted Knowledge improves its Powers, encreases its Liberty and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the Knowledge of God is an inestimable thing.</p>
            <p>Most powerful and merciful Lord God, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten the Day of thy Elect, when all shall rise from the dead and give an Account for their Works, in the time being, forgive my
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153879:9"/> Impatient Wishes, humble the Pride of the World, and the Enemies of thy sacred Truth, and accept my Hearty Thanks for thy Assistance in this Work, which I wholly attribute to thy Grace, and humbly dedicate to thy Honour. Let all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Magistrates consider, that when they have done judging others, they shall be judged themselves, and nothing shall be able to oppose the Decrees of thy infinite Wisdom, who hast made the Soul of Man of a refin'd Allay: Make every Man thankful, wise and faithful: Let us in every thing see thy Wisdom and Goodness: For every Rarity which thou hast made, is a Benefit to all, the holy Angels which have neither Ears nor Eyes, nor Tongues, nor Hands, are yet sensible Beings, and feel the Delights of all the World, and hear the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which not only Earth but Heaven maketh, the Melody of Kingdoms, the Joy of all Ages: These are all Objects of their Joy, they sing thy Praises for our sakes, while we are delighted by being made thy Gifts; a wise Man is the Joy and Blessing to all the Creatures, an Object of Delight to God himself, for the Nobility of the Soul, which is of Divine Extraction, capable of excellent Enioyments, even of admiring the Glory and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of God, wonderful are the Riches of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Wisdom; Oh let me see thy Splendour, and enjoy thy Divine Influences. I am transported with the Excellency of thy Love, thou art to me a shining Light, an exceeding Joy; thou hast given me thy self in all the Blessings I possess, I love the Happiness of all, I rejoyce in their Joy, and delight in their Glory; thy Wisdom enricheth every Gift, thy Love is eternal, thy Goodness infinite, thy Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty omnipresent, thou hast made Man in Thought and Action, an endless Treasure, in every thing thou overflowest infinitely to all, art infinite in Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in all thy ways, infinitely communicative of all thy Goodness; thou art divine, wise, blessed, holy, heavenly, glorious; I admire, I infinitely admire thy Riches and Wisdom; elevate my Soul
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153879:9"/> to a greater Knowledge of thee; make me more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Treasure of thy Wisdom; let no earthly Enjoyment encroach upon my Desire; trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form me to the Imitation of thy Wisdom; thou exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test those that are busie in thy Delight, thy Goodness reaches to every Soul in Heaven and Earth; teach us by Wisdom, Goodness and Love, to imitate thy Sweetness, and to enjoy all things as thou enjoyedst them; O thou that art the Light of the World, be infinitely profitable to us: The Light of Life to quicken our Sense, the Joy of Love to inflame us with Goodness, the Light of Knowledge, to make us see and understand divine things, the Joy and Treasure of our Souls; Jesus is the Purchaser of all our Glory; thy Affections here upon Earth were present with all Families, Kingdoms and Ages; let us with open Face behold as in a Glass, the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Lord, be transformed into the same Image! From Glory to Glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord, open to me the Gate of Wonder, Liberty, Difficulty, and also the Gate of Glory, Triumph, invincible Peace, unchangeable Goodness, Beauty and Delight; O Immortal Soveraign, let my Love be divine, invincible towards thee and all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble thy Divine Likeness: Cause me to seek the things that are above, and to disvalue earthly things; let me sacrifice my Mind to thee, by the renewing of the Spirit, let me offer to thee also my Body by a Chain of good Works, purifie my Body and Mind, and accept them in the Son of thy Love.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>LOrd prepare me for eternal Felicity, unlock the Mysteries of thy Divine Word unto me, that I may see the Treasure of Salvation; Learn how to please thee acceptably, and wisely understand the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Death, and be fully assured of a joyful Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ascend my Soul, mount up on Eagles Wings;</l>
                  <l>And get above these sublunary things:</l>
                  <l>Make haste, and fly unto that lofty Hill;</l>
                  <l>Where God abides with Saints and Angels still.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="deductions">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153879:10"/>
            <head>Some Deductions drawn from the First Eighth, 11, 15, 28 and 29 Articles of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article the First,</hi> Of the Holy Trinity.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THere is but one living and true God everlasting, without Body, Parts or Passions; of infinite Power, Wisdom and Goodness, the Maker and Preserver of all things both visible and invisible; and in Ʋnity, of this Godhead there be Three Persons, of one Substance Power, and Eternity, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article the Eighth.</hi> Of the Three Creeds.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE Three Creeds,</hi> Nicene (<hi>or</hi> Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan) <hi>Creed and that which is commonly called the Apostles Creed, ought throughly to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and believed; for they may be proved by most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Warran's of Holy Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Our Saviour was without Sin, both in his Flesh and Spirit, and we are accounted righteous only for his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi>
                  </q> Article 15. <hi>and 11. The Body of Christ is given, taken, and eaten in the Supper, only after an heavenly and spiritual manner, and the means whereby the Body of Christ is received and eaten in the Supper is Faith, Transubstantiation (or the change of Substance of Bread and Wine) in the Supper of the Lord, cannot be proved by holy Writ: But it is repugnant to the plain Words of Scripture, overthroweth the nature of a Sacrament, and hath given occasion to many Superstitions;</hi> Article 28.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article the 29th.</hi> Of the wicked which eat not the Body of Christ, in the use of the Lord's Supper.</head>
               <p>THE Wicked and such as are void of a lively Faith, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they do carnally and visibly press with their Teeth (as St. <hi>Augustine</hi> saith) the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Christ: Yet in no wise are they Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Christ, but rather to their Condemnation do eat and drink the sign or Sacrament of so great a thing.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153879:10"/>
            <head>Divine Meditations and Prayers, metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical and useful for the opening the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding and quickning Devotion, and instructing the Mind, and for the provoking Zeal for the Glory, Love, and Fear of God, and the Good of all Christians.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Most powerful Creator, speak Peace to my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, rebuke the Tempter, and raise me up to Newness of Life, crown the Queen's Majesty with all Royal Graces, make her wise as an Angel of God, bless the Nobles, Peers, and Judges of these Realms, with Wisdom from above, that they may rule as in thy Fear, by the Rule of thy Word; Look down in Mercy upon all the Children of Affliction, shine upon them with the favourable Beauty of thy Grace, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for divine Pleasures, in that glorious Place where eternal Comforts do flow. Enlighten all the desolate, with the Comfort of thy Sacred Spirit; O thou who art rich in Goodness, and thy Arms are open to receive thy poor Servants, receive to thy Protection all the afflicted, that draw near to thee, by true and sincere Repentance; Enter O Lord the Gates of my Heart, put a Watch over the Door of my Lips, that I speak not unadvisedly with my Tongue; let my Glory awake early in the Morning to bring Praises unto thee. Let the Ark of thy Presence rest within me, let no Sin reign in my Body, make me acceptably to praise and adore the Holy Trinity;</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>While I O Lord exalted by thy Hand,</l>
                  <l>Above the Skies in Glory seem to stand;</l>
                  <l>The Skies being made to serve me, as they do,</l>
                  <l>While I thy Glories in thy Goodness view.</l>
                  <l>To be in Glory higher than the Skies,</l>
                  <l>Is greater Bliss, than 'tis in Place to rise</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153879:11"/>
                  <l>Above the Stars: more blessed and divine.</l>
                  <l>To live and see; than like the Sun to shine.</l>
                  <l>O what Profoundness in my Body lies;</l>
                  <l>For whom the Earth was made, the Seas, the Skies;</l>
                  <l>So greatly high our Humane Bodies are,</l>
                  <l>That Angels scarcely may with them compare.</l>
                  <l>In all the heights of Glory seated, they,</l>
                  <l>Above the Sun in thine eternal Day;</l>
                  <l>Are seen to shine, with greater Gifts adorn'd</l>
                  <l>Than Gold with Light, or Flesh with Life suborn'd;</l>
                  <l>Suns are but Servants! Skies beneath their Feet,</l>
                  <l>The Stars but Stones, Moons but to serve them meet.</l>
                  <l>Beyond all heights above the World they reign,</l>
                  <l>In thy great Throne ordained to remain.</l>
                  <l>All Tropes are Clouds, Truth doth itself excel,</l>
                  <l>What ever Heights, <hi>Hyperbole</hi>'s can tell.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>LOrd enlighten my Understanding with the Comforts of thy Holy Spirit; make me constant in thy Fear; patient in Sufferings, and so establish my Heart, that no evil Tidings make me afraid. Let the Flames of Affliction render my Faith more pure, my Life more holy, and my Zeal more sincere and earnest; so direct me by thy Spirit, that I may at all times keep thy Commandments; enable me to walk before thee at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, with a pure Mind; moisten with heavenly Consolation all distressed Souls, that they may bring forth much Fruit; let Religion again recover its an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Lustre, double the Portion of thy Spirit on our Magistrates, that they may be just and rule in thy Fear, prosper thy Word of Grace, in the Mouths of thy Ministers; let the Doctrine of the Gospel run and be glorious; cause thy truth to shine gloriously; comfort all that mourn, let the Spirit of Glory rest on all those that suffer for the sake of Christ; Lord add Grace to their Hearts, that they may be able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, and to improve in all Goodness; Establish thy Law in all our Hearts, that we may sin no more; let thy Benedictions influence all my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, to direct us in the Ways of Light and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153879:11"/> Life; O Infinite God Center of my Soul, convert me powerfully to thee, that in thee I may find rest; my Heart is unquiet till it be united unto thee my God, thou hast given me a Body, wherein the Glory of thy Power shineth, <hi>fearfully and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made,</hi> give me a thankful Heart to admire all thy Works of Wonder; I adore thee for bestowing on me the Glory of Speech; Oh enable me to praise and celebrate thee, for all thy Mercies, for all the Beauties of Heaven and Earth; for the Melody of Sounds and sweet Odours of thy Dwelling-place; for the delectable Pleasures that gratifie my Sense; for the comfortable Light of Scripture and History, the Light of Heaven brought in by the Eye; I adore thy Goodness, who hast made me a living Inhabitant of the Centre of this great World.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord make us learn to wave even our own Right, for the Love of Peace, and to win others to be obedient to thee, by our Example. that our Zeal being discreet and mild, thou maist be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by these, and those that were scattered brought home to thee, for which cause we beseech thee, not to suffer us to censure others, at whose Condition and State we can but guess, seeing we hardly know our own Follies, that we plunge not our selves into eternal Ruine, nor afright from us thy holy Angels, whom thou hast appointed to be our Keepers, lest we come by our own Vileness to perish, and so contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict thy holy Will, who wouldest have none to be so unhappy, to which End thou hast given thy Ministry a supreme Power. In subjection to thy self, to bless in thy Name, even those that have formerly trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed thy divine Law, upon their Return to thee; O make us all with Humility and Fear come with humble Reverence to thee, for thou hast said, that he that comes to thee, thou wilt in no wise cast out, O make us all come to thee, with that reverential Fear, that may produce in our Souls a most firm hope in thy promises of our Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, grant us these Favours for thy Goodness sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153879:12"/>
               <p>O Lord we beseech thee to renew to us thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercies, which have been ever of old, and teach us the true way to thy heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that we may not miss of finding thee, O thou our all enlightning Sun, who hast promised to enlighten our Understandings, and illuminate our Wills, and make us conformable to thy heavenly Oracles; by being wary and reserved, chast and pure, holy and resigned to thy heavenly Pleasure in all things, that thou mayst teach us how to treat with every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Quality, not scorning our Inferiors, nor indiscrectly exalting them; but humbling our own Souls in every respect before thy great Majesty, that thou in thy due time mayst exalt us, that by our Service, and thy Mercy and Acceptance, we may gain the Wages of Eternity; that we may for ever with our whole Strength love and adore thee; yet still sincerely confessing, that I am an unprofitable Servant, yet depending upon thee always to relieve my Wants, and beseeching thee, that I may not forget to give thee to the utmost of my Power thy due Glory; O enable me these things faithfully to do, for thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy's sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord enable me first and above all to do thy will, that I may taste by experience, the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of thy Truth, and gain Courage to profess it even to Death; I beg thee to check our wild Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, that they may not disturb our Fancies, nor hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der free Reason from settling in our Minds; take away all willful Prejudice, that where Truth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails, we may yield to the Arguments of others, as ingeniously as we would they should yield to us, when we have Truth on our side, that we may be delivered from the rude Contempt of others, and from an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant Conceit of our selves, from blind Injustice of abusing Reason, that we may not gratifie Passion, nor give our selves up to bold Profaness, as those who wrest the sacred Scripture to defend their opiniated Errors, from the Guilt of which we beseech thee to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153879:12"/> deliver us, that our Souls may truly thirst after thee O glorify'd Jesus, and we may be admitted to drink freely of thy heavenly Sweetness, and grant that the Streams we gather here, may break forth and overflow into Rivers of living Water.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O good Jesus, the supreme Judge of Mercy, I beseech thee to give me true Repentance, and to that add thy gracious Pardon and powerfully save us, which we hope thou wilt do, because thou hast de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred our Punishment, in hopes of our Amendment, which comforts our fears because we hope thou wilt, absolve our Sins, O suffer not our Hope to be fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated, but graciously accomplish and fullfil our Hopes and Desires, for thy Mercy, Compassion, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Thou bright and glorious Light of the World, Illuminate our Souls that we may sincerely follow thee, and at last clearly behold thee in the Light of thy Glory; but in the mean time, cause me firmly to believe thee, and yet still more eagerly desire thee, to which Desire we humbly beseech thee graciously to answer, and to come immediately to dwell in our Souls, and there for ever love to inhabit. O my dear Lord, clear our Understandings, which are now dark and low, because our Conceptions of thee are Alass too dull and earthly; but blessed be thy Name, that thou hast now raised our Nature to believe thee, whose Words are mysterious and sublime, wherefore all thy Ways infinitely transcend our dull Capacities; blessed be thy Majesty for those little Glimpses thou hast given us of thy Greatness; O Lord be pleased graciously to give us further Disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of thee, that we may delight more in thee, that thou mayst be gracious and merciful to us, and deliver us out of all our Troubles and Destress, for thy Mercies sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>THy Service O Lord is the only true Liberty my Soul seeks after, and by thy Grace to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand our own Passions, is to be free indeed; O
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153879:13"/> therefore send thy divine Light into our Souls, and graciously govern our stubborn Nature, that we may not ignorantly mistake thee, nor willfully offend thee; left-thou shouldest give us up to the Simplicities of our own Follies, that will encrease still our irregular Appetite, and cause us to entangle our selves with sensual follies, which when we see by true Reason, our Souls abhor, detest and resolve to forsake; O en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us by the Power of thy Grace, to please thee for thy Mercies sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>WE need not go to enquire of thy Councels O Lord, to find the cause of our Calamities; Alass, our own Ingratitude is to plain a Reason, and our great and many Sins to visible a Cause; we are born most miserable, and our Miscarriages have encreased our Darkness, but we hope thou wilt in Pity relieve us for thy Glories sake, that the Works of thy Mercies may be manifested in us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou declarest thy Power most chiefly in shewing Mercy, wherefore we trust thou wilt cleanse us from all our corrupt Affections, that we may see and love thy Truth and Excellency, not daring to dispute when we find our selves convicted, nor fear openly to own our Faith, when we are called to confess it; O en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to be victorious even to Death, hoping thou wilt give us a Crown of Life, that we may joyfully sing Hallelujah with thee to the end of Eternity, O grant we may for thy Mercy's sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord keep us from such evil Intentions, as to cavil at some Circumstances, and deny the Substance of thy most sublime Truth; and open the Eyes of our blind Minds, that we may discern, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and love thy Excellencies, and make us think our selves blind enough to need the Guidance of the Wise; or be indeed wise enough to guide our selves, that we may enter by thee the Door of Life, and seed our Souls on thy Divine Joys for ever. O Lord deliver us from encreasing our Guilt by sinning against our Knowledge, and from hoping that our Ignorance will excuse our Guilt, because in us there
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153879:13"/> is most strange Perversness of Nature, but in thee O God wonderful Goodness; O therefore let us par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of thy Goodness, and then call us after thee, who art gone before to prepare blissful Mansions for us, make us worthy to follow thee, that we may for ever be happy with thee, in those blissful Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions above, to be filled with the Sweetness of thy Excellencies, and praise thee for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord, I know that the Applause of Men is but a vain Breath, and not worth regarding, much less the courting; therefore I will not seek for that, but my search shall be how to be truly worthy of thy Favours: For some Men can as easily dissemble their Praises, as others can counterfeit they deserve them; therefore by thy Grace I will neither covet nor value them, but diligently seek to please thee, O thou my Sovereign King, for thou only will I seek to be my Souls Director for ever, that I may always converse with a modest Calmness, and not passionately pursue things that deserve not our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, much less our Search; that thou mayst fortifie me with thy all-reviving Strength, to overcome all Lets and Hinderances that are in my Way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that I may become like thee in Will and Desire, and obtain that thou hast moved me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, the pure Robe of Christ's, Righteousness; and by thy Strength, never to defile this glorious Garment, but diligently adorn it by a holy Life; O enable me to persevere in Piety for thy Goodness sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord deliver us from every least Degree of uncharitably provoking our Neighbour, that we Imbitter not our Lives with mutual Animosities, nor make void our Piety by obstinate Willfullness, but cause us to obey the Rules of our wise Redeemer, that we may escape the Miseries that would spring from our Follies; O therefore suffer us not to set our Hearts upon any one sensual Pleasure, nor embroil our Memories with impure Thoughts, lest I should incur to my self thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity, or force thee to shower upon me thy Wrath, which I most heartily desire thee to divert and turn away for thy great Goodness sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153879:14"/>
               <p>O Almighty Creator, fill my Soul with some Beam of thy Excellency, who earnestly gaspeth after it, by the effectual Working of thy Grace in my Soul, O withdraw it not from me for thy great Goodness sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord relieve us, and give us of thy Strength, that we may constantly walk in the way of Life, by infusing thy Love into our Hearts, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing us to hold it fast for ever; that we may not loose our selves by neglecting thy Grace, for as thou hast bountifully relieved our Wants, suffer us not to forget to give thee Thanks, who renewest daily thy Mercies and Blessings to us, therefore make our Zeal for the Honour of thy Name, be discreet and mild, that we may have Peace O Lord with thee, and with all the World; esteeming greatly the Life of Innocency, and to converse in the World with a plain and candid Sincerity; laying open to thee all my Difficulties; beseeching thee to instruct my Doubts, and supply my Defects, that I may bear with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and Contentedness, and Thankfulness, all my unsuccessful Business and Endeavours, that I may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, love, and admire the Beauty of thy Truth, and the Praise of thy Name, which is great, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and holy; therefore to thee be Glory and Praise World without End.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord remember thy ancient Promises, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully urge them in favour of us Sinners, and heal us O thou heavenly Physician, whose Mercy both cures the Sick, and pardons the Penitent; and never fails to relieve with a generous Bounty, those who depend upon thee, therefore we will not pursue an empty Fame, but a Credit that may benefit others, that all may rise from the Death of Infidelity, to a Life of true Grace, to serve thee faithfully and truely with great Joy and Delight of Soul, and great Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord be pleased to check our wild Passions, that they may not disturb our Fancies, nor hinder free Reason from prevailing upon our Minds, but we may taste by experience the sweetness of thy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153879:14"/> Truth, that thou mayest move from my Heart all willful Prejudices, that we may yield to the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Truth and love it with clean Affections; that we may sweetly contemplate the Love of thy blessed Mercies to us, who hast filled us with a Desire of the Gifts of the Spirit, and to be cloathed with the real Substance of substantial Virtue, begging that we may not deat on the perishable Trifles of this vain World, but be studious to glorifie thee with all our feeble Power, never more resisting the charming sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of thy all-reviving Voice, but always adhering to thy blessed Commands, may become pleasing to thee and accepted of thee, that thou mayst put on us the Robe of Justice, and espouse us with the Ring of thy Love, and fill us with the Pleasure of thy Spirit.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Our Sovereign King, rule and command in us for ever, and so dispose all our unruly Motions, that they may conspire to set up thy Government, striving earnestly to practise all thy wise Precepts, instant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly answering thy Will with a quick Obedience, that thou mayst bless my small Endeavours with a great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, and cause the Relief we need to be conducive to our good, that we may give Glory to him, from whom all good things come, who causes us in the midst of Contradictions to trust in him, that we may still go on and perfect what we have begun, not doubting that our gracious Lord will defend and provide for us, helping us to correct at first those sudden heats of Anger, which would discompose us if they were not subdued, therefore subdue them, that they may not ruine our Souls, nor dishonour thee, nor scandalize our weak Brethren.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Thou great Physician of Souls, heal us, for our Souls need healing, and let nothing but thy Love find any Place in us, that our Lives may become one continual Prayer, quicken us with a ready Diligence to avoid every least occasion of Evil, and to embrace eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opportunity of Good, that always being guided by a cautious Prudence, we may repair our lost Innocence, and past Negligence, by our present and most hearty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and future Watchfullness, that thy Grace may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153879:15"/> enable us to follow thee in the Regeneration, that thou mayst accept us in the general Day of Mercy, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord Write all thy Holy Truths in our Souls, and Print thy Love in the Centre of them; and there let it sit Soveraign Governour, and absolutely dispose all our Interests, let it command my Tongue to confess thee, that no Fear of Danger may cause me to deny thee, nor any Derision of Man cause me to lessen my vigorous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in thy Service, that by thy Grace I may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all Difficulties, and know how to manage my self wisely in every Affair, to thy great Glory and my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Good, that I may valiantly without Fear, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake all that prejudices me in my Way to this Happiness, depending wholly upon the Fidelity of my Soveraign Lord, that after this Life I may be worthy to praise him incessantly World without End.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Jesus, thou hast abundantly done for us all the kind Offices of a faithful Pastor, for thou hast laid down thy Life to redeem us, and taken it again for our everlasting Comfort, and hast exalted our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by raising thy self from the Dead, and placing thy self at the Right Hand of thy Father in Glory, by whose kind Intercession we also were reconciled to thy Father, and by whose Merits our Necessities are freely supplied, and our feeble Hearts supported, our Friends blessed, and our Enemies vanquished and subdued, because whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he did was for our Good, therefore I will heartily strive to magnify and adore him with all my feeble Power and Might, for he is worthy of all Admiration, therefore to him be Glory and Praise World without End.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>HOW beautiful O Lord are the Feet of thy holy Messengers, who brings us Peace and Reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thee, teaching us the Way to eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, who by their pious Offices help us in our Way thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; O teach us in Love and Gratitude freely to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them with temporal Necessaries, as a Token that we heartily embrace their Doctrine, and rejoice in the glad Tidings thereof, shewing all the World by our pious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, that we believe the Gospel, and rejoyce in the Publication of it, passionately wishing that all the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153879:15"/> World would obey it, by living by the Rule of it; O give them Grace to square their Lives by this blessed Rule for thy Goodness sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord teach me to triumph over my own Passions, that thy holy Comforts may ravish my Heart, so strengthen me that I may triumph over my Enemies, that I may live so inoffensively, that my Name may be enrolled in Heaven, and I may immediately run to thee who so kindly invitest me, because thy Burden is light, and thy Yoke most easie, thou refreshest the Labours of all that approach thee, with reverential Fear and humble Love, make me worthily approach thee in due manner, and then be pleased favourably to accept me for thy Mercy sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord I am deeply sensible that it is not the Name and Dignity that any one bears, can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title him to Heaven, but the real Disposition of the Soul to do good, neither is it the Affections of our Friends and Kindred, that can excuse and satisfie our Duty, but our Exercise of Love to thee, and to all for thy sake, even to all that need our Assistance: O give us all ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and compassionate Hearts, to assist, relieve and comfort all that lies within the compass of our Power, for thy sake, and to thy Glory, and their present Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, in order to their future Good.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord prevent us from being perplexed with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary Cares, that our Minds be not distracted with a multitude of trifling Provisions, but let us seek chiefly the one thing necessary, that chusing that best Part, we may for ever be happy, that we may not at any time be disturbed with our own Disquiet, but he sweetly filled with Peace, contemplating thy great and infinite Mercies, that our Love of thee, and those holy Joys thou hast prepared for us may be greatly encreased, that our Lips may still repeat thy Praises with fresh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, that thou mayst continue to us the Multitudè of thy Mercies, and we may still more and more admire and adore thee for them, with all our Souls Might and Strength, that thou mayst graciously accept us for thy Mercies sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153879:16"/>
               <p>O Lord suffer us not to give over praying, till thou art graciously pleased to regard and answer us, teach us for what we ought to pray, &amp; give us only those things that are fit for us to receive, for we know that it is in Mercy that thou deniest us many things we are apt to desire, therefore now we beg to be guided by thee in all things according to thy blessed &amp; all-knowing Wisdom, and good Pleasure, wherefore if I have but little in this World, give me Grace to be humble and industrious, seeking (above all) the pleasure of the celestial World where we shall not want for Honour, Wealth, nor real Love; O fill us with thy heavenly Love, that we may in some Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure be fit for that kingly and bleffed City, and be of that happy Number that admires thee eternally.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord grant that I may never value the fair Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in the Eyes of others, before the real Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Virtue, nor more affect some petty Devotions than the Fundamental Laws of Justice and Charity, nor yet be so foolish as to place any Felicity in the vain Esteem and Glory of the World, nor be so boldly prophane as to affront my Maker by an impious and lewd Life, lest Religion thus abused, should prove to my Ruin, for Pride must be humbled, and Hypocrisie confounded, but from the Guilt of these I beseech thee to deliver me for thy Mercy and Compassion sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord we know thy Power is irresistable, and thou hast also promised, that it shall defend us, therefore will we not fear what Man can do against us, seeing the only thing we desire is to be rich towards thee, for Wealth consisteth not in abundance of Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, but in thy Favours, therefore let me learn that vain and uncertain are the Projects of this World, and very dangerous are the best Enjoyments of this Life: I heartily and humbly beg Grace, that I may first and above all, seek earnestly the Treasure of Heaven, for I desire no Treasure but that which is with thee, O admit me to be an humble Sharer of that Felicity, for thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord I beseech thee to inflame our Souls with the Fervour of thy Love, that we may earnestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire for ever to dwell in thy Presence, delighting our selves with the blessed Exercise of Prayer and Praise,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153879:16"/> that thou mayst bestow on us the full Streams of thy ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Mercy, who needs nothing to move it but the sight of our Miseries, O therefore remember thy ancient Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and pity me, and suffer not my Faith to be weakned by the many Divisions and Distractions that are in the World, lest my Charity should grow cold through the Weakness of my Faith, or my Hope be made faint through the Indisposition of both, but fill me with hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Virtue and Courage, that may cause me to be truly wise to Salvation, and thy Wisdom may be so powerful as to cause me to confute the Power and Malice of my Adversaries, that I may serve thee with a free Will and ready Mind, to the utmost of my Strength and Power, to my last Breath.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord grant that whatsoever my Enemies have done through Malice, in Scorn and Derision of me, thy Pity may turn and repeat to my Honour and Advantage, but let not my Enemies be punished with an impenitent Death, but give them true Repentance, and deliver them from the Malice and Dominion of the Enemy of their Souls, suffer them not to provoke thee to Anger any more, but give them Grace to please thee both in Will and Deed, that their Souls may be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally saved, for thy Mercy and Compassion sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord comfort us and our Enemies, when the Hour of Death approaches either to them or us, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously repeat to them, and us, at each of our Departure, thy sweet and heavenly Consolations, this Day shall ye be with me in Paradice, &amp; let the Thoughts of our own Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture melt our Hearts into tender affectionate Wishes and Prayers, for those who are at all times near the Approaches of Death: O be present with them then with thy sweet reviving Comforts, and suffer them not for any Pains of Death, or Anguish of Sickness to fall from thee, but in their Weakness be thou strong to enable them to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all Temptations, that by thy Mercy their Souls may become precious in thy Sight, and thy holy Angels may bear them into thy Presence, to admire and praise thee for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord prevent us with thy special Grace, and put into our Minds good Desires, that by thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153879:17"/> Help, we may bring the same to good Effect, through the Merits and Satisfaction of Jesus our Dear Redeemer.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O The strange Efficacy of Heroick Virtue, that were the Lives of eminent Believers truly and exactly good, their Example alone through the Mercy of God, would convert the World, for this would efficaciously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Vices of the great, and meekly instruct the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the People, and earnestly exhort every one to repent, then would none resist the Sweetness of the blessed Jesus's Voice, who spreads forth his Wings, though Multitudes refuse to be gathered unto him; Pardon, O our dear Redeemer, our strange Ingratitude, and leave us not desolate to be ruined by our Follies, suffer us not to be so dismal, as to enure our selves any longer to sin, lest one Enormity prove the Punishment of another, and our own Folly bring us to eternal Ruin, but this be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to prevent for thy Mercy and Pity sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord make me as humble in my own Eyes, as I am werthless in thine, O suffer me not proudly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for my self before others, nor enviously murmur, that they are preferred before me, that I may not be frustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of my Hope, in the Resurrection of the just, but give me Grace so to walk, that in that great Day I may be worthy of thy Acceptance, and with great Comfort, hear that blessed Sentence of <hi>Well done good and faithful Servant, enter thou into thy Masters Joy.</hi> O grant me to be worthy of this great Blessing and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, for thy Mercy and Compassion sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Love of Loves, that is most generous and pure, aiming chiefly at the Happiness of thy Servants, O my dear Jesus let nothing divert me from embracing and obeying the Dictates of thy blessed Love, that I may by no means aspire too high, nor lazily sit down in a slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gish Life, but with a faithful Prudence take measure of my self, and trust in thee my dear Lord; to bless and prosper my Endeavours, for I know most assuredly that thy Grace is sufficient to make me victorious, and thy Glories all-sufficient to repair all my Losses, though I am too weak to overcome my Enemies, and too imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect to delight in Affliction, yet by thy Help and Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153879:17"/> I will endeavour patiently to bear all Crosses and Afflictions, that shall befall me, hoping thou wilt cause them to work together for my Good, that thereby I may more earnestly strive to glorifie thee in all things, O as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist me in so doing for thy Goodness and Pity sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord I heartily desire to mourn over my Sins with true Contrition, and to be revenged on my Follies with a Life of Severity, that I may be worthy to put on the Robe of Justice, and to re-espouse my dearest Lord with a Ring of Love, and feast him with the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Joy of a pure Heart: Oh be pleased to accept me, and cause me never to forget thy former Mercies, but mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thee at the Return and the Remembrance of them, with all the Powers of my Soul, that when this my House of Clay shall fall into the Dust, my Soul may be received into the Tabernacle of everlasting Joy and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity to praise and admire the King of Glory, for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord quicken me with a ready Diligence to avoid every the least occasion of Sin, and embrace every Opportunity of thy Service, that we being inured by thy Love, may always delight therein, that we wisely chusing by thy Directions, may be always exercised in heavenly Business, till it shall please thee to advance us thither, to admire and adore thee for ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord suffer me not to seek undue Redresses, in the Troubles incident to my Condition, nor vainly amuse my self with Desires of Change, but earnestly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to remove from me all Impediments to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, that thy bright Glory may crown me for ever with lasting Honour, in that durable and most plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant Kingdom, where I beseech thee to advance me to admire and adore thee for ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord suffer me not to be any more so slow to begin my Prayers, nor so swiftly without heed run them over, nor so coldly propose to thee my Wants, nor so quickly weary in renewing my Petitions, but O my dear Lord, cause my Life to be one continual Prayer, that in every Step I tread, I may grow strong in the Power of thy Grace, and of thy Spirit, and pursue the eager Designs of enjoying thy bright Glory, grant this for thy Mercy sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153879:18"/>
               <p>O Lord suffer me not to be of so impure a Spirit, as to desire the Revenge of my Enemies, but let them and me become thy Friends, that I may be thy faithful and devout Servant, that we may all be inured to wear thy Yoke, striving to be Imitators of thy own Meekness and Innocency, that we may all avoid the Temptations of this Life, by a cautious Prudence, and repair our lost Innocence by a hearty and a deep Repentance, that we may all be true Lovers of thee, by fullfilling thy Law, by walking in the Rule of Heroick Virtue, not setting our Hearts upon any thing but thee, because if we love any thing above thee, it is impossible to be eternally hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: Therefore O Lord remove from us all impure Loves, that we may love thee with our full Souls, Might, and Strength, O grant that we may speedily do so, for thy Mercy and Compassion sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Thou of infinite Bounty, give me of thy all-sufficient Grace, that it may direct me to the true Way to Glory, that I may not lose my Day in Idleness, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract my Diligence with repining at the Abundance of others, since thou art our absolute Lord, and givest to all as thou in Mercy pleasest: O give me Grace to look upon my present Condition, as thy immediate Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and be heartily thankful to thee for it, unless my Ingratitude should render me unworthy of future Favours; but of this Crime suffer me never to be guilty for thy great Names sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord heal all our Infirmities for thy Mercy sake, and invigorate our Souls with thy divine Grace, that in all our Actions, our chief Aim may be to thy Glory, for which we pray thee to quicken our Faith, and strengthen our Hope, and encrease our Charity, and so order and guide our Steps, that in all things we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have our selves like good Christians, that if ill Men persecute us, we may prudently avoid them, and if our Friends reject us, we may go quietly from them, that whatsoever befalls us we may never study Revenge, but evercome our Enemies evil, by our good Actions, that so by the Practice of Heroick Prudence, we may win many to thy Obedience, that obeying thee in Heart and Mind, we all may be admitted to dwell with thee eternally to adore and praise thee forever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153879:18"/>
               <p>O Lord when we are approaching thy Service, let us go with unusual Swiftness, that we may find our selves overwhelmed and swallowed up with Joy therein, that we may be worthy to be exalted to wear a Crown of Glory, even that Crown which thou hast promised to the Perseverers in Virtue; O enable me worthily to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severe therein, to thy Honour and my immortal Good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord who dost govern all things both in Heaven and Earth, mercifully hear the Supplications of thy People, graciously look upon our Infirmities, and in all our Dangers and Necessities, stretch forth thy Right Hand, to help, defend and comfort us with the Blessings of Health, Peace and Plenty all the Days of our Lives, through the Merits of Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord give me Grace to watch and study the Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of others, while I enjoy the Sweetness of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Life, that thou mayst not give me over to so vile Affections, as to repine at those who are advanced above me, but I may in all things content my self with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou allowest me, that thou mayst invite thy self to be my Guest, and I may carefully prepare for thee a Lodging in my Soul by the help of thy assisting and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Grace, which I beg thee not to suffer me to be destitute of, for thy Mercy sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord suffer me not to be discouraged at the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of my Infirmities, give me Grace to strive against all my natural Corruptions, by earnestly corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them by the divine Aids of thy Grace, and the Arts of the wise Methods thou hast prescribed us, that thou mayst invite thy self to be our Guest, and come and lodge with me, and for ever there inhabit: Cloath my Soul with the bright Beams of thy Light, and illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the whole Frame of my Affections, my Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, my Mind and my Will; that I may gladly rejoice in thy Service, with my whole Heart and Soul.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord deliver me from thinking my Sins can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by Alms, or my Trespasses satisfied by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Restitution, or an Intention to for sake them; for I know it is not that which can expiate for my Guilt, but the Merits of my dearest Lord alone, who do require
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153879:19"/> in me a thorough Reformation, with new Obedience to which I will add my earnest Care, that it may be my chief Study and Practice, that I may please thee both in Will and Deed, to the utmost of my Power, through thy blessed Assistance, which I beg thee not to suffer me to be destitute of, for thy Goodness sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O my dear Lord, permit not any loose Companions to divert me from thee, neither let the Noise of the World drown my Prayers, but let me lay hold on every good Opportunity to serve thee, that I may become thy Child by Adoption and Grace, and may be truly rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, and daily renewed by thy Holy Spirit, that all Vice may be mortified and killed in me, and by the Power of thy Grace. I may gain the Victory over all Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, that passing through this World with Courage and Constancy, I may have a joyful Reception in the other, and with Chors of Saints and Angels adore thee for ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord suffer me not to envy the good Works of others, nor seek Pretences to undervalue their Merit, but give me Grace to honour and value them, because thou hast bestowed on them the true Circumcision of the Spirit, and caused them to walk by the Rule of Life, O give me Grace also to imitate them, for the Merits of Jesus my dear Lord and Master.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord let the precious Odours of the Saints still em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balm thy holy and most sacred Name, and spread their sweet Perfume over all the World, that by their Example, the present Age may still go on, and throughly perfect that Good which thou hast begun in them: O therefore always defend, and at length reward them: For Jesus sake, Cast the bright Beams of thy heavenly Light upon the whole Church Militant, that it may be more and more enlightned by the Doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, that every Person may walk in the light of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Life, and gain the Victory over all their Vices, by Virtue of the true Circumcision of thy holy Spirit, and thereby both perceive and know what things they ought to do; and have Grace and Power faithfully to do the same, through the Merits and Satisfaction of Jesus Christ our Lord, to whom with the Father and the Blessed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153879:19"/> Spirit, be all Honour and Glory, World without End.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>BLush O my Soul at the Thoughts of Pride, and be confounded at thy vain curiosity, lest thy Lord dazzle with Brightness thy impure Eyes, that have so often beheld Vanity and Folly; but now I desire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect my Thoughts, and become a new Creature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching thee to keep me continually in thy true Religion, that I leaning only upon the hope of thy heavenly Grace, may evermore be defended by thy mighty Power, from all Evils that might happen to the Body, and from all Assaults that might molest or hurt the Soul, through the Merits and Satisfaction of Jesus our dear Redeemer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord consecrate my Heart entirely to thy Service, and throughly purge me from all Impurity, that thou mayest enter into my Soul, and there for ever abide, and I may be in some Degree worthy to glorifie thee, and that I may be so, suffer me no longer to be affected to the World, that I may not be subject to the Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, which thou hast for us overcome; O therefore suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer us not to bring our selves into his Bondage, but give our selves up to be guided by thy gracious Conduct, for this is my Hearts Desire, and my Souls Request; therefore stretch forth the Right Hand of thy Majesty, to be my Defence against all the hostile Assaults of my Enemy, for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Two following Prayers are Preparatory for the Holy Sacrament.</head>
               <p>O Lord let us never resist thy Grace, lest thou shouldst take it from us, but let us desire to partake of the Pleasures of a virtuous Life, that we may always feed upon the Pleasures of a good Conscience, for that with thy Comforts is the continual' Feasts that we desire to feed on, that is a most heavenly and blessed Banquet; by this together with Faith, thou makest thy Son himself to be our delicious Entertainment, O so prevent us, that we may never disregard or neglect to admire this great Mercy, for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Most amiable Jesus, my Lord and my God have Mercy upon me, be my Comfort thou Refuge of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and grant that the Holy Sacrament which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend devoutly to receive, may be to the Remission of all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153879:20"/> my Sins, and the strengthning of my Soul in good Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, the perfect purging away all my Faults, the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing all impure Thoughts, and the begetting good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires in me, that I may plentifully bring forth the Fruits of Life.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord soften our Hearts, that we may turn to thee and be healed, that thou mayst not give us over for Reprobates, nor to a reprobate Sense, but make our Faith quick and active, that we may sacrifice all the Faculties of our noble Souls to thee, that thou mayst purify our Intentions sincerely to seek thee, that we may in thy due time find everlasting Rest to our Souls, ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy Wisdom where we do not understand, and loving thy Goodness, which we have long time experienced, striving earnestly to be worthy of thy continuing it to us, O grant that we may be so, for thy Mercy sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord I wholly rely on thee, therefore I beseech thee to send me speedy Comfort, and turn all my Affronts and Afflictions into present Refreshments, and make me Partaker of thy merciful Clemency, that I may be filled with thy admirable Meekness, and continue no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger so strange and ingrateful, nor study to escape thy pressing Arguments, nor shift off the Truth when I see it convinces me, nor any longer debase my Reason, but endeavour to bring my Desires and my Mind to suit with thy Will and my present Condition, that by thy Grace, I may have such Strength of Mind, that I may by thy Assistance overcome all Difficulties, that we may carefully do all that is fit to be done in order to our ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Good, &amp; grant that we which know thee now by Faith, may after this Life have the Fruition of thy glorious Godhead, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord I beseech thee favourably to hear the Prayers of thy People, that we who are justly punished for our Offences, may be mercifully relieved by thy Goodness, and by thy Power be defended from all Adversity of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul; thou seest that we put not our trust in any thing that we do, but depend only upon the Hope of thy heavenly Grace; O encrease those heavenly Graces in us, for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:153879:20"/>
               <p>O Lord reprove in all People the Sins of the Spirit, and give them of thy Strength, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come easy to repent, and suffer them no longer to refuse to be obedient to the gracious Motions of thy Blessed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that the corruption of their Nature may be subdued, and they persevere in Virtue, and discern the Season of Grace, and no more follow the Dictates of their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse Minds, that thy speedy Mercy may give them all spiritual and temporal Good, with a speedy Supply of whatsoever is wanting to them, that by the Virtue of thy Grace, they may immediately imitate thy ancient followers, and not conceal, but publish thy Mercies with all their Might, and use all means possible for the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of their Minds, straining all their Powers to move thee to pity them, that by thy comfortable Relief, they may in some Degree be worthy to admire thee for ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord by thy Wisdom confound the Malice of Men, and the Conspiracies of Hypocrites, whose De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulness tends to the Ruin of others, and the Dishonour of thee; but most of all to the Destruction of their own Souls; O therefore reprove them in time, that they may repent in Season, before the Day of Grace is past, and be brought to submit obediently to thy Truth, and resign and capacitate their Understandings, to be truly submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive and obedient to the wise Dictates of thy blessed and most heavenly Pleasure, and cause them to sacrifice all their noble Faculties to thee, and kindle in their Hearts an earnest Desire of thy Presence, and a firm reliance on thy holy Protection, that when they are in the greatest Danger, thy merciful Hand mayest save them; O grant them these Favours for thy Goodness sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Lord convert the World, and make them worthy to be hereafter as the holy Angels, perfectly knowing thee, and fervently loving, and admiring, and adoring thee, that thy Knowledge or Joys may not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to a few petty Instances, but let them and us possess the true Obieck of our Love and Knowledge, grant this for thy great Majesty sake. O our dearest Lord, who fillest Heaven and Earth with thy Power and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Wisdom and Clemency, therefore to thee be Glory and Praise, World without End.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153879:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Holy Jesus, how incomparable didst thou argue to confute those that erred, and patiently forbearest to say they had erred, till thou hadst confuted them, and after all with unprovoking Words reprovest them and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missest them, and all this thou didst for a Method to teach us Charity, by the Art of practising those things thou taughtest, <hi>O</hi> teach us this thy wise Method to solid Virtue, that we may be directed by the Assistance of the Holy Ghost, and secured from falling by the Presence of the Holy Jesus, of whom we hope to be endowed with Power to overcome all Difficulties by the Help of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting and assisting Grace, by which we beseech thee to put into our Minds good Desires, that by thy conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Mercy, we may bring the same to good Effect, through thy Merits and Satisfaction <hi>O</hi> Blessed Jesus, to whom with the Father and the Eternal Spirit, be all Honour and Glory, World without End.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord endow me with Power from above, to do whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is well pleasing in thy Sight, in the Multitude of thy gracious Mercy, Regard and accept my little Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance; tho' it be weak and imperfect, yet I beg thee to make it sincere for thy Mercy sake. Prepare my Heart to receive and believe thy Word, that I may be worthy that it may have an abiding Place in me, that I may be blessed with the true Felicity of serving thee, and with that Freedom of overcoming and commanding my own Passions, that our Understandings may be no longer so dark and low, but heartily bless and praise thee, for raising our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to believe in thee, and in thy Word which is most mysterious and sublime, and infinitely transcends our dull Capacities; yet so it pleaseth thee to illuminate our Souls, imprinting in them a Desire to obey thy Will, who art the Judge of Mercy; therefore grant that at length we may behold thee in the Light of thy Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord make the Poor so sincere, that their Service and small Offerings may be preferred equal to those that are rich in Grace and good Works; give us all Grace, that we may not puzzle our Thoughts with more Curiosities than may conduce to our Improvement, nor be so blindly unjust as to abuse our own Reason, nor be so rude as to contemn others, nor to have arrogant
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153879:21"/> Thoughts of our selves, but may think humbly and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of our selves, as knowing our selves truly unworthy; yet firmly trusting in thy kind Acceptance, through the Satisfaction of our great Master Jesus, to whom with thee <hi>O</hi> Father and the Holy Spirit be all Honour and Glory; World without End.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord give us Grace to fly to thy Mercy; that we may escape the Severity of thy Justice, by which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to deliver me from severe Extremities here, and from eternal Vengeance hereafter; shew me that am in Error the Light of thy Truth, and give me thy assisting Power, that I may return into the Way of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, that I may be admitted to the Fellowship of thy Heavenly Kingdom, by eschewing those things that are contrary to my Profession, and following all such good things as are agreeable to the same, that I may lean only upon the help of thy heavenly Grace, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord suffer not my Weakness to be over much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed with too heavy Afflictions, lest I sink under the too heavy oppressing Load of them, but submit in all things to thy Blessed Will, and not presume to grow im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient when we are told our Faults, or what displeaseth us, neither to be so unhappy as to think our selves better than others, since we know not what thy Mercy <hi>O</hi> God may esteem them, or to what Divine Honour advance them, nor what thy Justice may do with us, but devoutly beg Mercy for them and us, that we all may be accepted of thee; <hi>O</hi> make us worthy to ask this of thee, and with speed answer our Petition for the Glory of thy great Name.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord grant that from our own Experience, we may learn to rely on thy Divine Providence; for every one of us sees from the Variety of Accidents, the great and pressing need of thy Assistance, for 'tis not our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure that can make us either rich or happy without thy Blessing; nor our own Arm nor the Assistance of Friends that can defend us, without thy extraordinary Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, therefore we beg it of thee, <hi>O</hi> deny it not for thy Mercy sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Pastors of the Church.</head>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:153879:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAnctifie</hi> O <hi>Lord the Pastors of thy Church, and make us duly to respect them as the Preservers of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; Illuminate their Understandings with the Light of Knowledge, and inflame their Wills with the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of thy Love, that their Lives may shine before us, and we by our Obedience may follow them, that their Example and our Obedience may bring us to thy Glory;</hi> O <hi>Lord accomplish thy merciful Benignity towards us, and let thy heavenly Grace govern every Creature, and bring every one to the true way to Beatitude, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may disturb our Peace nor ruine our Innocency, but we may publish thy Power in every place, and by thy Strength we may conquer all our Passions, and follow thee in all things, the great Example of our Peace and Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, who wilt pity our Frailty and not take Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of our Weakness, therefore Glory be to thee for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord inure us betimes to break off our Affections to this World, and to place them on thee, and thy Joys above, to which blessed Place thou hast so sweetly invited all that truly obey thee, <hi>O</hi> how ravishing is this gracious Invitation, and how full of reviving Comfort is that blessed Palace, which is prepared for the Just, <hi>O</hi> make us exactly righteous that we may be in the number of those whom thou wilt impute eternally blessed, when thou <hi>O</hi> blessed Judge wilt endearingly proclaim to all the World, the Virtues of the wise and prudent, <hi>O</hi> make us prudently wise to Salvation for thy Mercy and Pity sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord suffer not my Patience to be tempted above my strength, but give me of thy all-meriting Power to overcome all Obstacles in my way to Heaven, deliver me from all Deceitfullness, that my Faith may not be eccli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>psed, but I may be delivered from slumbering in a Life of Carelessness and Indevotion, let us watch in the Day of our Strength against every evil Way, that we may not be snared in a Course of Wickedness or Impenitence, but may be mercifully delivered from all Sin and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by thy speedy Grace, that no Snare fall upon us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, but having faithfully cultivated our Souls by thy Grace from all that is evil, we may be accepted by thee, and received to admire and praise thee for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:153879:22"/>
               <head>A Prayer for the Queen's Majesty, and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Magistrates.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord keep our gracious Princess from being ecclipsed with evil, or oppressed by Enemies, and with Her, bless all inferiour Magistrates under Her; that she and they may perform their several Offices to thy Glory, and their own immortal Good; that when they depart this Life, their Souls may be eternally happy, with thee <hi>O</hi> our dear Lord for ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord give us of thy Strength to watch in our decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Years, against all the many Snares of Satan, that our decrepid Age may not be overcome nor circumvented by his Subtilty and Craft, nor we be so foolish as to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire after things prejudicial to our Souls, but consider that Honour is vain, and Authority troublesome; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will seek chiefly and above all, to aspire after the Glories of Heaven, accounting every thing trivial and troublesome, that is a Let or Hinderance to our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Arrival thither, because we desire passionately to be Favorites to our dear and only Lord, to whom be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory World without End.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Bright and Glorious Scene, the Son of God great in Majesty, infold us within the Arms of thy Mercy, and prepare us for that glorious Kingdom, which thou hast mercifully prepared for us, before the World was. <hi>O</hi> how are our Hearts ravished at the Thoughts of our Arrival thither, all thy Counsels are sweet and easie: <hi>O</hi> give us Grace gladly to receive and obey them, that we may always walk by thy Directions which are clear and safe, <hi>O</hi> guide us still to follow them, that we may not fail of being brought to the Blessed Mansions above, to enjoy thy blessed Presence for ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord have Mercy upon those, that have shewed no Mercy to others; O how will their Faces be covered with Confusion, when their base Ingratitude will be published to all the World; O Lord reserve some Pity for them, by smiting their Hearts in this Life, before they go hence, in order to their through Conversion; suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them not to go on in their evil Dealings, lest they perish for ever, but over power them with thy Grace, that they may not be the Ruin of their own Souls, therefore
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153879:23"/> cause them to be throughly converted to thy self, that thou mayst include them in the Number of those whom thou shalt impute blessed, that thou mayst sweetly invite them to live and reign in the blessed Mansions above, for ever; O grant them these Mercies and Favours for thy Goodness and Pity sake <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>O Merciful Lord, wash me throughly from my Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and wipe away all my Iniquities, and say to my stubborn Soul, be humble and I will be thy Comforter, wherefore I will not despair of thy Grace, but with a prudent Fear suspect my self, and with an humble Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence rely on thee, whose endearing Wisdom has divised an infinite and all-sufficient Remedy for all my Offences and willeth that every Creature that thou hast made, be improved to Perfection, therefore I will remain no longer incorrigible, but banish and depart from all my Sins, that the holy Ambition of being happy in Heaven, may extinguish all immoderate Esteem of the glossy Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of things below, and aspire in earnest after things above, that we may not affect any thing in comparison with thy self, that no mutual Animosities amongst us, may at any time dishonour our Religion, nor cause us to derogate from that excellent Virtue, which thy self hast chosen to be the Badge of a Christian, nor our Faith ever fail, but grow and encrease to fill us with Charity and all other Graces anticedent to Glory, grant this for Jesus Christ his sake <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord infuse thy Holy Spirit into my Soul, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully govern all my Faculties with thy heavenly Grace, that by my Love to thee I may obey thee, and by thy Love be made uncessantly to admire and adore thee, whose clear and perfect Vision is my only Felicity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I long and desire passionately to be with thee, O in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease these Desires in me, till thou shalt be pleased to change these Desires to perfect and unvailed Vision, and Fruition in the Kingdom of Glory <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Thou who seest and notest the first Motions of our Hearts, and grantest to us (sometimes) our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest when we are but going to ask; and showerst down upon us the Multitude of thy Blessings, when we in Slumber and Inobservance takes no notice of them, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153879:23"/> comes to us in our great Oppressions to chear our Hearts, staying with us and affording us his Presence, even when we are unmindful of it, and unthankful to him for it, and when he is pleased to withdraw and retire from us, he is pleased to send us his Holy Spirit, to supply his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, therefore to him be Glory and Praise for ever and ever <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Holy Jesus, who didst all things for our Experience, and wheresoever thou wentest, 'twas for our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; make us firmly resolve to amend our vile Course, that all thy holy Actions may not be lost upon us, nor prove invain to us, and suffer us never to forget our good Purposes and holy Resolutions, but by thy Grace en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to renew our good Purposes and Intentions, and bitterly bewail our Sins and Infirmities, and at length gain the Victory over them, that we may gain thy blessed Favour, and continue in it for ever <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord let us not grudge that the World frowns on us, but with serious Thoughts consider that it did not smile on thee; who mad'st it, and yet dost uphold it and all things in it; O give me Courage and Fortitude to resist all that would oppose me in my heavenly Race; but yet O my dear Lord, expose me not to great Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, lest my Strength fail, and I cannot be able to overcome; neither suffer me to be stricken where my Weakness lies, but give me of thy Strength to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by thy Grace, that I may win the Crown of Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord suffer me not to be so monstruously ingrateful, as to forget the great Mercy thou hast, and daily dost bestow on me; lest I cause thee to withdraw them from me, but cure thou my Ignorance and supply my Necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and let no Grain of Ingratitude abide in me, but chace it from me for thy Mercy sake <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Make me truly thankful to thee, for all thy Favours bestowed upon me, in giving me Health, Food and Rayment, and Friends; and for placing in me a hearty Desire of being eternally happy, and that not without the true means an innocent and a blameless Life: To this add true Devotion, and cleanse me throughly from all my Sins, by the Merits of the precious Blood of thy dear Son, that I being cleansed from all my Sins, and made
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153879:24"/> passionately devout, may with meek and silent Patience, expect thy second appearing in Glory <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Thou whose Love surpasseth Mans Ʋnderstanding, and causedst thee to be numbered amongst the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressors, that we might be numbered among the Saints, and drink of the pure Streams which flow from thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Kingly Throne. Suffer us not to be Abusers of thy Favours, lest we are deservedly forsaken by thee; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we beg Constancy to please thee, to the end, that by thy Mercies we may walk cheerfully and constantly in the way of Life, that thou mayst relieve and comfort us, and support us to continue in thy heavenly Ways, that we may taste of thy heavenly Treasure in this Life, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy glorious Beauty in the other <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord depart not from me, for without thee I faint and die, neither let me depart from thee by Sin, lest I die eternally; but while we continue in this World, keep us in thy Favour, that in the other World we may dwell with thee for ever: Preserve me O Lord from all Danger, by thy Holy Grace, and when thou art pleased to call me hence, translate me to heavenly Glory, that I may for ever seed on that comfortable Love, which begun before thee World was, &amp; will continue when it shall be reduced to nothing; let this Love of thine, confirm and increase in me all good Works, that I may plentifully bring forth good Fruits, to the Honour and Glory of thy great Name, through Jesus Christ our Lord <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Lord fill my Soul with the eternal Dew of thy holy Spirit,</l>
                  <l>That both my Body and Soul may eternal Life inherit.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>PRepare thy self O my Soul seriously to consider the strangest and truest Tragedy that ever drew Tears from the sad Spectators Eyes; even thy dearest Lord! after his entring the fatal Garden, where he continued all Night in Prayer, sweating Water and Blood, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards nailed to the Cross, where he hung Three long Hours, and all for thy sake, that no Torments might touch thee; therefore trace and follow him through all the Stages of his Misery, and leave him not till thou seest him ascend up into his Glory, that as he suffered, so
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153879:24"/> his Mercy may find Pardon for thee, not leaving thy drousie Nature to it self, but endeavour to make it watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that his Majesty may visit it with his holy Grace, and quicken it with his blessed Spirit, and keep it wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king constantly with his blessed Presence, that it never more consent to dishonour thee by Sin, but may glorifie thee in every Action of Life, always delighting to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versant with thee, that thou mayest delight to be present with me to my Lives end, and then gather me to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, full of good Works, to remain with thee for ever <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord give me Grace constantly to renew my entire Submission to thy gracious Will, that I may renew the generous Charity of my great Master Jesus, and his free Submission, together with his incomparable Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that no fair Pretence may tempt me to offend thee, but let me remember that horrid Fact, Christs Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion, the Cause of which I deeply lament, let me not have Cause to endeavour to hide my self from thee, when I ought with all Reverence and Submission to adore thee, O aimable Meekness, that my Soul may be cloathed with the Robes of Justice and Righteousness, and both Body and Soul be made fit for thy heavenly Kingdom, and admitted to enjoy perpetual Pleasure with thee for ever and ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord thou needest not our weak Aid to bring about thy ends, for thou with the Word of thy Power, canst command all created things to obey thee, wherefore no thing can conquer thee, but thine own invincible Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; and this indeed brought the Holy Jesus captive to the Hands of his Enemies, and caused him to submit even to Death for our sakes, that we might not remain in Death; but be Conquerors with him over Sin and Death, and be thought worthy to be admitted to eternal Life, grant this O Lord for thy Bounty and Compassion sake <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Thou the alone and all-wise Goodness, chuse for me what is well pleasing in thy Sight, that I may not be peremptory; nor incorrigible under any Affliction thou shalt please to lay upon me; but wisely resign my self to thy wise Providence, to be wholly guided thereby, that I may partake of thy admirable Meekness and Clemency,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153879:25"/> my Thoughts being firmly fixed on my future Hopes; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove whatsoever is amiss in me, and teach me true Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and cause me to hope with eagerness for thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that I may possess them with Gladness <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord grant that my Affictions may be sanctified to me, that they may be the Cause of the Increase of Virtue, and a Way that leads to an eternal Crown; but suffer them not to be a woful Beginning of never-ending Miseries, but make me live so uprightly that I may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the Greatness of thy Power and Mercy to Eternity, and I may praise thy aimable Power and Goodness with all the Chors above a numberless Number of Ages <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord break through my Deafness, that I may hear thy Voice, and fear thy Power, and most readily obey thy Will, that I openly confessing my Sins, may glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and readily declare thy infinite and inexhaustible Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which by happy Experience I have found so long comfort me; proceeding alone from thee the only Author of all Good, and the Beginning and End of all our Hope, therefore to thee be Glory and Praise, World without End <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Thou chast Spouse of Souls, quicken our Hearts with thy divine Charity, that all our Powers may unite to seek thee, and with a swift and fervent Constancy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severe, till we find thee, that we may win the rich Crown at the End of our Race; quicken therefore our Affections after thee, and suffer us not to remain so dull seeing we are pursuing the Glories of Heaven, therefore let us not be soon weary, nor easily diverted from this happy Search, but let us nimbly move, seeing the Reward of thy Love is great, who hast faithfully promised that we shall reap the rich Comforts thereof; O hasten the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of that happy time, for thy Mercy sake <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord bestow on me a zealous and an active Spirit, that I may be quick of Apprehension to do thy Will, and ardent in Affections after the full Enjoyment of thee, O fill us all with Solidity of Soul and Mind, to do in all things what is well pleasing in thy sight, through Jesus Christ our Lord <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <p>I have divided the following Pages into Twenty Eight Chapters.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:153879:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>